<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of the apology of Socrates Christianus, or, A plain declaration of the authority by which he acts freely offered to the consideration of all serious, considerate, and unprejudiced Christians.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5439A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42855</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875851</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152415</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152415)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2296:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of the apology of Socrates Christianus, or, A plain declaration of the authority by which he acts freely offered to the consideration of all serious, considerate, and unprejudiced Christians.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens by Wing [2nd ed.].</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing 2nd ed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Religion and politics --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152415:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="title">
               <p>The Second PART OF THE APOLOGY OF Socrates Chriſtianus; OR, A Plain <hi>Declaration of the Authority,</hi> by which he acts; freely offered to the Conſideration of all Serious, Conſiderate, and unprejudiced Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <p>IT was not to Conceal my own <hi>Name,</hi> that I aſſum'd that of <hi>Socrates Chriſtianus</hi> at the firſt: For that I never did my ſelf, or deſired my Printer ſhould, from any who deſired to know it. But having long ſince purpoſed never to Print my Name with any thing I ſhould Publiſh (unleſs for ſpecial neceſſary Cauſe) I aſſumed that upon Occaſion of the <hi>Manner of Writing</hi> I then uſed: And that I have reſumed it again now, was not without ſpecial Cauſe from the Compleat <hi>Agreement obſervable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Caſe and my own. His Apology</hi> Conſiſts of <hi>two Parts:</hi> In the one he refells the Lyes, Calumnies and Falſe Accuſations brought againſt him by three Principal Adverſaries; <hi>Melitus</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of the Poets (generally <hi>Latitudinarians</hi>) <hi>Anytus</hi> of the, Craftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and <hi>Politici</hi> (a Proper Name of the ſame Sect) and <hi>Lycon</hi> of the Orators and Sophiſters (as truly <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> as any.)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152415:2"/>Theſe were the Men, who raiſed the Clamours, and ſtirred up the People againſt <hi>Socrates;</hi> and have all revived to act their part in my Caſe. But I thought it ſufficient to refell their Falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and Calumnies without noting the Perſons, ſince they have not appeared openly, but under hand againſt me. And this part I hope I have done to the Satisfaction of all Honeſt, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial, and Intelligent Perſons: As for the reſt, their <hi>Weakneſs</hi> is to be pitied, and their <hi>Raſhneſs</hi> and <hi>Reproaches</hi> to be born with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Encouragements of the Religion we Profeſs, till Mrs. <hi>Experience</hi> convince them of their Error, and how much they are abuſed.</p>
               <p>In the other part he declares <hi>by what Authority</hi> he did thoſe things which he did; and that no leſs than Divine Authority; That it was <hi>a Duty impoſed upon him by God;</hi> that he was <hi>by God Appointed to the Care and Over-ſight of the City, and conſtituted Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perviſor thereof.</hi> It is now near Seven Years ſince I, being to fulfil all Righteouſneſs in receiving Commiſſion (ſuch as could be had here) from Men, was ſolemnly demanded in the Preſence of the People, to Anſwer this important Queſtion: <hi>Do you truſt that you are inwardly mov'd by the Holy Ghoſt, to take upon yon this Office and Miniſtration, to ſerve God for the Promotion of His Glory, and the edifying of hit People?</hi> Which I ſhould never have anſwered in the Affirmative as I did, had I not been fully ſo perſwaded; or had I had any doubt either concerning ſuch <hi>Motions</hi> in general, or of ſuch ſpecial Motion in my own Caſe, and to that very Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, I was then to engage in. And being well ſatisfied of ſuch a <hi>Divine Call,</hi> I durſt not refuſe it for any Scruples at the other; Nor do I think fit to deſert that Service now, for any Defect of Humane Authority I have ſince diſcovered; though I confeſs I would not have refuſed to have had thoſe Defects ſupplyed by competent Ordinary Authority, notwithſtanding any Temporal Laws againſt it, if it might have been upon ſuch Terms, as I could have ſubmitted to. But ſince that could not be, I am well ſatisfied with that, which is moſt <hi>Neceſſary</hi> and <hi>Eſſential,</hi> and as much beſides, as the Legal Clergy of this Nation can pretend to.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>the Caſe</hi> be as I take it to be, there will appear more in it, than, for ought I know, any Man elſe in this Nation can pretend to. Almighty God had appropriated the Prieſthood under the Law to the <hi>Tribe of Levi,</hi> yet <hi>Samuel,</hi> who was not of that Tribe, Miniſtred before the Lord, Girded with a Linen Ephod, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.18. and offered Sacrifice, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7, 9, 17. It was indeed an Extraordinary Caſe: His Mother had dedicated him to the Lord,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152415:2"/>and the Lord accepted him. He, who obligeth others to his Ordinance, doth not thereby always oblige himſelf: And he that grants a General Commiſſion to many, may notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding grant a ſpecial Commiſſion to one, if he pleaſeth, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſpecial Occaſion. I preſume not to ſay this is my Caſe; or how far it is ſo, I leave that to others to judge upon due Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Particulars I have to relate. And I hope <hi>Socrates Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus</hi> may ſind as much Credit with true Chriſtians, as <hi>Socrates Philoſophus</hi> with Infidels and Apoſtates.</p>
               <p>What <hi>my Mother</hi> did for me, I cannot ſay; but ſhe was a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Parts and Piety, and all I remember of her is only part of a Prayer ſhe taught me, That God would make me <hi>an Inſtrument of much Good in his Church, and in the Common Wealth;</hi> but this I might have ſaid, <hi>When my Father and Mother forſake me, the Lord taketh me up.</hi> For I remember neither; yet this I remember ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, that when I was a Boy the very Names of <hi>Wiſdom and Virtue</hi> were Precious to me: But no particular inſtructions do I remember, to which any ſuch <hi>Impreſſions</hi> might be imputed. Though I was ſtudiouſly inclined and loved <hi>Retirement,</hi> yet was I always very ready to <hi>appear and Act</hi> for the Service of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, or of my Friends; and, when but fifteen years of Age, went to ſerve the King with as much Sincerity and Pure Zeal as any one could. Before I was twenty, I applied my ſelf with much Guſt and great Satisfaction to the Reading of the Antient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, the Antient Philoſophers, and the Spiritual Writers. And when I was about thirty I knew experimentally the Myſtery of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates his Genius:</hi> And while I heedfully obſerved that Conduct, I lived in a Bleſſed Condition; All my Affairs ſucceeded with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Eaſe, as in a manner done and diſpatch'd to my Hand; and I had ſuch Anſwers to my <hi>Prayers</hi> for People in Difficult and Dangerous Caſes, as were little leſs than Miraculous. But I never did any thing contrary, though with all the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Care I could uſe, and the beſt Advice of Friends I could get, but it proved very unſucceſsful and unhappy. But in this my <hi>Notices</hi> were ſomewhat different from thoſe of <hi>Socrates;</hi> for they were as well <hi>To</hi> ſome Actions, eſpecially to Prayer, as <hi>From</hi> ſome others. And once I was ſo unhappy in Diſobedience to one of thoſe, that it was like the Sin of <hi>Adam</hi> to me, and the In-lett to all the Unhappineſs, which hath ſince befallen my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and I had preſently upon it as ſenſible Notice of it, as if it had been a Sentence declared againſt me: And much of that Favour hath ever ſince been withheld front me.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152415:3"/>
               <p>Before this, near forty years ſince, I think it was, or rather more, that in the next Pariſh, where was a great Family of my Relations, I perſwaded and prevailed to have THE HOLY COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MUNION Celebrated <hi>Monthly,</hi> which was rarely then any where elſe in the Nation, above once, or twice, or thrice at the moſt in the Year. Afterwards when I removed to another Pariſh, where I was both Lord of the Mannor and (as we call it) Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of the Church, I not only continued <hi>Monthly</hi> Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, but at laſt brought it to <hi>Weekly;</hi> and it ſo continued till I had occaſion to remove thence for my Health to a City, where it was then ſo Celebrated. Nor was I ſatisfied with this, but being frequently at <hi>London,</hi> I wrot to the then Arch-Biſhop <hi>Sancroft,</hi> that it might be Ordered to be <hi>Daily</hi> in one or two Churches about <hi>London.</hi> And my Letter was well taken by the good man, though it was not done, whatever it was that hindered it. But at laſt, when I had little or no Hopes of what I had ſo long De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, it pleaſed God to grant me my deſire in a <hi>Surpriſing man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I had brought back a Perſon, who had been Ordain'd according to the preſent Church of <hi>England,</hi> from the Diſſenters, to frequent the <hi>Early Communion</hi> at St. <hi>Laurences;</hi> and I had ſent to the place, where he was ordained, and had a Certificate of his Ordination from the Regiſter; but not in the leaſt then thinking of what after followed. But returning one Morning from that Early Communion with him and ſome other Devout People, I over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard one of them ſaying ſomething of the Comfort and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit they found in it: Whereupon, I replyed, Ay, what would ye ſay to have it ſo <hi>every day?</hi> And when ſeveral of them decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how glad they ſhould be of ſuch an Opportunity, I replyed again, that if they were in good earneſt, I knew how it might be; for there was one in the Company, who to my knowledge was in Orders according to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and would, I doubted not, be willing to Officiate. And thereupon we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to meet at his Houſe at Night, and there farther agreed to begin the next Morning that DAYLY COMMUNION, which has been continued ever ſince with many as <hi>ſurprizing Steps</hi> under the ſame Sacred Conduct, by which it was at firſt begun. This was in Autumn 1692.</p>
               <p>I had before this left off my <hi>Profeſſion of the Law:</hi> After that had received a Providential <hi>Qietus,</hi> as I apprehend it, from ſome other things, wherein I had, <hi>Socrates</hi>-like, endeavoured to ſerve my Country: And I had alſo <hi>forſaken the World,</hi> and ſettled all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152415:3"/>my Eſtate upon my Wife and Children, as abſolutely as I could, without any Reſervation whatever, caſting my ſelf wholly upon the <hi>Providence of God,</hi> without any thoughts of any thing more than a Solitary Retirement: And I have by that Providence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince been ſo provided for and Conducted, as to me hath been far beyond all the Enjoyments of the World, and all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Wiſdom whatever. Our little <hi>Society</hi> was <hi>begun</hi> upon theſe <hi>three Principles;</hi> To <hi>meet every day early at the Holy Communion;</hi> To <hi>follow the Example of the Ancient Christians, as near as we can;</hi> and, <hi>To avoid all Offence, as much as we may.</hi> It was begun at his Houſe who did firſt officiate: but after a little time, ſettle in another, mean and diſpicable, but very convenient Place, and where we enjoyed that Serenity and Satisfaction, which is not commonly to be met with in Princes Courts, or the Palaces of Great Perſons in the World.</p>
               <p>But it was not long before the Perſon who did officiate, was removed from us, and I my ſelf brought into ſuch Circumſtances, that I neither could, unleſs I would let the Work I had been ſo much concerned for, ſo long promoting, and was ſo far enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in, fall to the ground, nor durſt refuſe to <hi>take Orders,</hi> to which I was invited, and not only led by a <hi>ſurprizing External Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,</hi> but alſo obliged by ſeveral <hi>Internal Motions,</hi> both correcting my Reluctance, and encouraging my Submiſſion. And after I had done this, and had begun to officiate my ſelf, it was not long before we were as unexpectedly and ſurprizingly led from our private Lodgings, to perform that ſolemn Service in a <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church,</hi> and of one of the greateſt Pariſhes, of the City, but without the Walls: And after ſome time, to <hi>another,</hi> juſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Walls, ſomething leſs, but much more to our Satisfaction, by reaſon of its Privacy. But neither were we permitted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long there; Nor could we obtain the uſe of any <hi>other,</hi> by any Means we could uſe, but <hi>in the very Heart of the City:</hi> And both the Services being more than I was able to perform, we had no other expedient, but were forced to meet daily at eight of the Clock at <hi>Bow,</hi> and then to walk thence along <hi>Cheap-ſide</hi> to St. <hi>Matthews,</hi> as if on purpoſe, that what we did, might the more be taken Notice of, whether we would or no. And then I began to be ſenſible what <hi>our Buſineſs</hi> was, to which were led by ſo many <hi>ſurprizing Steps</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Secret Conduct;</hi> viz. to bear <hi>a Tacit Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony for God</hi> againſt the common wilful Neglect of that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Worſhip, which we there performed, in all other Parts of the Nation.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152415:4"/>
               <p>It was my deſire to reſtore this Holy Worſhip of the <hi>Chriſtian Sacrifice,</hi> not only to its due <hi>Frequency,</hi> but alſo to its juſt <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity,</hi> which had been much deformed and diſordered by <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> and his Foreign Agents, though I knew not then by whom, or what Practices it was done, only perceived that it was ſo; and therefore Compoſed a <hi>Form</hi> as near as I could to the Mind of the Antients, but taking in all the Common Form; and had a few Copies Printed, which we uſed, while we continued at our Private Lodgings. But this I could not expect would be permitted to be uſed in a Publick Church; and therefore I was forced to uſe the Common Form, only ſupplying what I could from other parts, and reſtoring what had been diſordered, to the proper places. And yet this was not eaſily permitted, till being Queſtioned for it, I was to make my Defence, the ſame good Providence, which had ordered the Buiſneſs all along, brought (as ſeaſonably as unexpectedly) to my hand one of thoſe <hi>Book,</hi> which were <hi>Compoſed for the Church of</hi> Scotland; under the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, and with the Approbation of the Engliſh Biſhops, in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. as compleatly agreeable to my mind, as as if I had done it my ſelf; and not long after, the firſt and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy, compoſed by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy in the Reign of K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. but wickedly deformed by <hi>Cranmer</hi> and his Foreigners, and his deformed Changeling, Schiſmatically obtruded upon the Church, by the Parliament, without the Conſent of the Clergy in the Convocation, inſtead of it, which was the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, from which that for <hi>Scotland</hi> was taken. Upon ſight of the firſt of thoſe, I printed my Defence, which I had before ſent only in writing to the Arch-Biſhop; and not long after, when I had met with the other, <hi>The Liturgie of the Antients repreſented, as near as well might be, in</hi> Engliſh <hi>Forms; with a Preface concerning the Reſtitution of the moſt Solemn part of the Chriſtian Worſhip, to its Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and juſt Frequency:</hi> and preſented it to the Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop of <hi>London, &amp;c.</hi> uſed it in the Church, and offer'd to ſtand a Tryal with any that would queſtion me for it, notwithſtanding the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 14, <hi>Car.</hi> 2. againſt it.</p>
               <p>But there I continued the uſe of it between two and three Years, and might undoubtedly have done ſo till this day, if I had thought fit: but that I did not, conſidering how unworthily and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully it was neglected by the Clergy: there being in the firſt Church we uſed no leſs than three in Prieſts Orders, and not one of them ever came to join with us, unleſs the Reader once or twice at the moſt: and there, after their Preaching and Printing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152415:4"/>for frequent Communion, they not only after ſome time, put a ſtop to our daily Communion, but reduced their own from weekly to monthly: In the next Church we had, we never had any of the Clergy, but once two, who came upon a ſpecial Occaſion: and then again after ſome time, upon ſome little Temporal Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, we had Warning given to remove within a time limited. In the third place indeed, the Dr. liv'd at a great diſtance; but he was always kind to us: but then it became more known, we had Communicants, who came frequently from all Parts, and for ſome time ſeldom ſo few as thirty daily, and on the Lord's Day and other Holy-days, a conſiderable Number; but not above three or four times any of the Clergy; but on the contrary upon Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-days, another Communion was ſet up at <hi>Bow</hi> he Arch-biſhops peculiar, in oppoſition, as I ſuppoſed, to it; and others falling off, till we were not ordinarily above twenty, I began to think we had done our Buſineſs, and <hi>finiſhed our Teſtimony;</hi> and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Neglect, I wiſh'd for a Diſcharge from that Publick Place, fearing it might be but expoſing of ſuch Holy things, if continued much longer; yet did not think fit to leave that Station without either ſome <hi>Prohibition</hi> to proceed, or ſuch <hi>Invitation</hi> to ſome other as might ſatisfy me to do it: and ſuch an one we had ſoon after, and a very conſiderable one indeed: but the only Effect of it was firſt <hi>a Satisfactory Diſcharge</hi> from that Publick Service, and next a <hi>Review of the Reformation,</hi> for which I had a Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Retirement, and other Considerable Advantages; and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives ſufficient before I left the City. And of the Obſervations I made upon that Review in Relation both to Church and State, I gave ſome Account to ſuch as I thought moſt proper.</p>
               <p>And here again we had another Admirable Evidence of that Wiſe and Gracious <hi>Providence,</hi> by which this Work had been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered all along: For we had certainly been involved in much Trouble and Difficulties, had not the ſame infallible Providence both foreſeen it from the beginning, and as ſeaſonably and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently provided for it. But the ſeveral <hi>Manifestations of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Conduct</hi> over us to this time, are more than need to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, or can be ſo ſenſibly underſtood by ſuch as were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in them, or have had no Experience of the like. Nor perhaps was it neceſſary that it ſhould ail be ſo manifeſt to any other as, to my ſelf, who was to Act, and yet do nothing which needed any <hi>Extraordinary Authority,</hi> or Atteſtation for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of ſuch as were concerned in what I did. But it ſeems to have been providentially ordered, that ſo much ſhould be ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152415:5"/>manifeſt to me, as is ſufficient not only to ſatisfy ſuch <hi>Scruples</hi> as might be raiſed in my own Mind, but alſo to anſwer the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections</hi> of others.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Principal Objections</hi> are againſt my Performance of the <hi>Office of Priesthood</hi> without other Ordinary Authority, than what I my ſelf now think not ſufficient. But to the <hi>Political Clergy,</hi> who make this Objection, I anſwer; 1. That for Ordinary Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority I have as much as themſelves: 2. That that was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for ſome purpoſes, and particularly for a tacit Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt them: 3. That I have beſides what doth ſatisfy my ſelf; and that, whether Ordinary or Extraordinary, is ſufficient for them: And to <hi>all others,</hi> that I take not this Office of my ſelf, but was <hi>called of God,</hi> as <hi>Samuel</hi> was; firſt Dedicated to his Service by particular Dedication (if not by my Mother, which might be too, for ought I know) however, by my ſelf, which is not leſs, and accepted by him; and this manifeſted by an <hi>Extraordinary Concurrence of various Cauſes,</hi> many of them in a ſurprizing and yet orderly and neceſſary manner, to the producing of ſuch juſt, reaſonable and neceſſary <hi>Effects,</hi> as our Daily Communion; my Engaging in that Service; our Performance of it under ſuch a Conduct from deſpicable private Lodgings to the very Heart of the City; and then there, for ſo long time, a ſufficient time, without any Interruption, notwithſtanding the Laws againſt the Form I was known to uſe, Then my Diſcharge in due ſeaſon, and to my Satisfaction; and our Conduct thence to a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Place of Retirement; with ſeaſonable Proviſion for unſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Difficulties; and our Reduction back again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo many Circumſtances ſo orderly concurring, as can no more be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for without a Providence, than an orderly Compoſure of proper Letters, into a Verſe or Sentence without the Skill of a Compoſitor and a Founder: and beſides, all this <hi>Structure</hi> built upon the <hi>Foundation</hi> of a <hi>Conſtant Diſpoſition</hi> of ſo many years Continuance, to what neither any thing in Nature, nor any Temporal Proſpect was any Motive or Inducement: and farther yet, my Acceptance of the Office not without ſuch ſpecial <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Motions,</hi> as I had had Experience of many years before, to what the Laws of the Land require, ſo that I could with clear Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience anſwer the Queſtions to be propoſed to me. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of all theſe, 1. Of ſuch a <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> of ſo many years Continuance; 2. Of ſo many External <hi>Providential Occurrences,</hi> ſo neceſſary, ſo orderly ſucceeding, and in ſo ſurprizing a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Such <hi>Internal Motions:</hi> And all to the ſame juſt, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152415:5"/>reaſonable, and neceſſary <hi>End;</hi> is to me ſo <hi>Satisfactory</hi> an <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> as I can hardly think can be rejected by any one, who doth not disbelieve either a Divine Providence, or at leaſt, one of the Chief Principles of the Goſpel; but think ſufficient for <hi>Caution</hi> to all conſiderate Perſons, and for <hi>Conviction</hi> before God of ſuch as preſume to oppoſe or diſpiſe it.</p>
               <p>If my <hi>Commiſſion</hi> be defective in the <hi>Ordinary Conveyance,</hi> whoſe Fault is that? But may not that Defect be ſupplied by what is <hi>Extraordinary?</hi> Is God's Hand ſhortened? Has our Saviour limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Power by His Commiſſion to the Twelve? How then came <hi>Paul</hi> to be an Apoſtle? Is there not as much need now here, as there was in the days of <hi>Samuel</hi> then? Conſult Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> Conſult Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> Conſult Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Famous Cathedral, in the Principal City of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in his laſt Chapter of Religious Aſſemblies, and others that might be named. Are not many Teachers either ſhamefully Ignorant of the moſt Solemn and peculiar Part of the Chriſtian Worſhip, or notoriouſly ſelf-condemned here, and in danger to be damned hereafter for their unfaithfulneſs, and wilful Neglect of what they know? And is not ſuch an <hi>Admonition</hi> highly <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> in ſuch a Caſe and very <hi>ſuitable</hi> to the Methods of the Divine Wiſdom and Providence?</p>
               <p>And for <hi>the rest of my Buſineſs,</hi> what is it, but what is a Common and Ordinary Duty? The Service of God, The Service of my Country, the Reformation of Manners; the Preſervation of Peace by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving the Seeds of Diſſention, and great Occaſions of Wars, and making that impregnable which is now indefenſible; the Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Genuine Primitive Chriſtianity; Healing the Breaches of the Church of Chriſt, and promoting the Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its Rights by Aſſertion of Truth, neceſſary Truth, and ſuch Truth as all my <hi>Adverſaries</hi> are not able to gain-ſay or reſiſt. Nay, does not their very <hi>Dealings with me</hi> at the ſame time both diſcover them to be of the Spirit of the <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> and Atteſt and Confirm <hi>My Miſſion,</hi> as a true Diſciple of Chriſt? This is <hi>My Buſineſs</hi> to aſſert and bear My <hi>Testimony</hi> to the <hi>Truths of God</hi> in ſuch Manner and Order as he is pleaſed to order and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect; and thoſe not any <hi>New Revelations,</hi> but the Truths once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints, and received by the Churches; Catholick Truths, oppoſed by none but <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and <hi>Falſe Teachers,</hi> who corrupt the Doctrine of the Goſpel, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify their own Luſts, and to pleaſe the People; who can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concernedly behold the <hi>Growth of all Sects,</hi> even of' <hi>Infidelity</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152415:6"/>
                  <hi>Apostacy,</hi> and notorious Oppoſition of all revealed Religion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Notion of <hi>Deiſm</hi> and <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> except only ſuch as they think (like themſelves) aim Chieſly at their Cathedrals and Preferments. This is their <hi>Diana</hi> for which they are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and for which they can eaſily <hi>join and combine with Infidels, and Deiſts, and Commonwealths Men,</hi> to ſecure that againſt ſuch as they think may lay Claim to it: And ſo they can but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that, they can willingly enough give up one part of the reſt to the State, and the remainder to the Sects; nay be well appaid to have their Paſtoral Charge performed by them, ſo they may but quietly enjoy the Revenues and Profits to themſelves; and upon Confidence of ſuch Aſſiſtants without either Shame, or Scruple of Conſcience, or Fear of Scandal, hold ſuch <hi>Charges at inconſiſtent diſtances,</hi> as good Chriſtians here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore would have dreaded to undertake but one of them. And certainly their ſo great <hi>Concern</hi> in the one Caſe, and ſo little Concern in all others of Religion (of which the inſtances which might be given are undeniable and notorious) is ſo ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, that it is not to be doubted, but it is one of the greateſt <hi>Temptations to Atheiſm and Deiſm</hi> that is in this Nation: For the <hi>Scandals</hi> of the moſt groſly Scandalous is nothing ſo effectually Scandalous, as ſuch as appears <hi>under Sheeps Cloathing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was my <hi>plain Reproof</hi> of theſe things, and charging them with <hi>Filthy Lucre,</hi> that firſt provoked an <hi>Angry Letter</hi> to my ſelf, then the <hi>Appeal</hi> ſent me in a Penny-Poſt Cover, then that <hi>falſe and fooliſh Letter,</hi> elſewhere mentioned, and at laſt that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and Loyal <hi>Combination</hi> of <hi>Latitudinarians</hi> with Deiſts and Commonwealths Men, of like Concern in the State, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Church; and all that <hi>Noiſe and Clamour,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the People have been abuſed, the King affronted, and all good and ſolid Methods, and the Advantages, which the good Providence of God had put into our hands at this time, for a Happy Settlement of a laſting Peace both in Church and State, madly diſturbed, and the Peace of the Nation greatly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered, unleſs more Prudent Counſels and better Courſes be taken in time. And indeed what <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> may not reaſonably be expected from a <hi>Combination of two ſuch Factions;</hi> if they be but a little animated at the firſt, either by Authority, or, which is more to them, by an inconſiderate, well meaning, abuſed Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple! Of the <hi>One</hi> we have had Experience enough within our own Memory; and they have given the Nation a fair Warning of what they would be at now again, by a bold attempt to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152415:6"/>the Anuual Memorial of it, by a very Virtuous and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Preacher of Mr. <hi>Toland</hi>'s Club upon the Thirtieth of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> which I hear is ſometimes viſited by a like Virtuous Chair Man of the ſame Party in his Chair; A very proper and ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Preparative for ſo furious reviving the old Pretence, from which that day at laſt became ſo Memorable. The <hi>Other</hi> is as very a Faction too; and that appears by like Practices to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their own Deſigns, in keeping <hi>the Convocation</hi> from ſitting and acting: For did they not know that the greateſt part of the Clergy of this Church are againſt what they would have, and in Matters of no ſmall Moment, they would never be guilty of ſo foul a Practice. And that it is done by their Perſwaſion or Miſinformation and Encouragement, doth likewiſe appear by the Anſwer to the Letter to a Convocation Man.</p>
               <p>And how foul a thing this is, will appear, if the Manifold Evils apparent in it, beſides what may be latent and not yet diſcovered, be well conſidered: 1. It is a <hi>Betraying</hi> of the <hi>Rights of the Church</hi> of Chriſt, and <hi>Eſſential Rights,</hi> as to its being one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and a formed Society: 2. It is a Betraying of the <hi>Rights of their own Order,</hi> and Rights <hi>abſolutely Neceſſary</hi> for the Diſcharge of their Duty in common to Conſult and Adviſe concerning the Great and common Concerns of the Church. 3. And this is done at a time of as great need as ever, of an Aſſembly of the Clergy; when Immorality is grown to that height, that all the Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> did not dare to bring in a Bill, drawn at their own Requeſt, and peruſed by able Counſel, and all the Judges then in Town, into the Parliament to ſuppreſs it; and to that Impudence that a Notorious Scandalous Cauſe, and of one in Great place, hath not only been defended in the Courts of Law in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> but at laſt brought by Appeal before the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and no notice of the Scandal, though undeniable, taken by all or any of the Biſhops, as if there was nothing of Diſcipline left in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and Impiety to that height and Impudence, that one of their Lordſhips hath complained to me that they are put to prove their Creed, and the fifth Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew:</hi> But a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er inſtance than this I have lately given in my Letter to Sir <hi>R. C.</hi> which hath produced only a more notorious Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. 4. This Antichriſtian Treachery is ſo peculiar to this Faction, that I know no Sect beſides themſelves that is guilty of it: Nay what they deny to their own Brethren, they themſelves will not deny to any of the Diſſenters, nor ſo much
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152415:7"/>as to the Quakers, though Conſtantly, Annually Notorious and complain'd of, 5. It is an injury to the whole Body of the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> joyned with Abuſe and Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery (in Effect;) and repeated and continued for many years together: For what elſe is it never to let them Sit and Act, when they are ſo often Call'd and Aſſembled?</p>
               <p>Nor, 6. Are the Miſchiefs to the State and Government, leſs than theſe to the Church. They betray the State into Sin by encouraging a Uſurpation, which is one of the greateſt Acts of <hi>Sacrilege</hi> that can be; and that by as Groſs and Pernicious an <hi>Hereſy,</hi> condemned by all Parties but their own Faction; and beſides are charged with <hi>Schiſm</hi> by a Conſiderable Part of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who make out ſufficiently by ſtrength of Argument, what they want in number of Perſons. But of ſuch Latitude are their Principles, that they comprehend as great Matters as all this, as juſtifiable, or excuſable enough, for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their End, and therefore one of them, <hi>Melitus</hi> himſelf, who firſt began the Clamours, could tell me, <hi>Do you think that King</hi> William <hi>will part with ſuch a Flower in His Crown?</hi> Yea, ſay I, why not? and with his Crown too for juſt and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cauſe, if he be indeed a Chriſtian. But they who are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo much for getting and keeping, that they can ſtrain their Conſciences for it, cannot eaſily believe that others will be perſwaded to part with what they have once gotten, upon any Terms or Conſideration. Such Flowers to the Eye of a worldly minded Man, are to a Chriſtian indeed no better than Weeds, ſtinking Weeds, and are really Poyſonous Weeds in their Effects. And certainly it is no more conſiſtent with the Duty of a faithful Paſtor of Chriſt's Flock, than of a good Subject and true Friend to his Country, to ſuffer his Prince to take ſuch Poyſon without Warning. But what wonder if they, who make no ſcruple to betray the Rights of Chriſt's Kingdom, make as little to expoſe their Prince and Country too to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for their own Ends? And what elſe do they, who encourage a Prince, whoſe Title is doubtful, or it may be, none at all in the Judgment of his Neighbours, to do and continue what is offenſive to ſo conſiderable a part of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and caſt the Odium of their own Evil Counſels upon his Will and Pleaſure, to the Prejudice and Scandal of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? The <hi>Engliſh</hi> are an Active and Bold People, and as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the Violations of their Rights as any: And when they are free from Wars abroad, are not like to be very quiet at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152415:7"/>Home, upon ſuch Occaſions and Provocations. And <hi>Rights of the Church</hi> have in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws been always heretofore as carefully provided for as any, and particularly in the <hi>Corronation Oath.</hi> And <hi>the Rights of the Convocation,</hi> which are well vindicated in a Learned Book lately publiſhed, are ſo well underſtood by many Learned Men of this Church, that I wondered that none did it before, or that the Univerſities and the Clergy of the ſeveral Dioceſſes, did not by ſome Publick Inſtruments, declare their Judgments, or at leaſt revive the Antient good Cuſtom of <hi>Communicatory Letters</hi> in much uſe, when under Heathen Emperours they could not enjoy the Liberty of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods to Conſult of the Common Concerns of the Church. But I hear of another coming out; and more may reaſonably be expected if this Courſe be ſtill continued. Surely it is time both for the Clergy, and for the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> the Commons, I ſay, not their Truſtees, eſpecially ſuch as are notoriouſly known to have made a Trade of their Employment, to look about them; for I do not apprehend that the Chriſtian Religion and the true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment can be in greater Danger than from <hi>two ſuch Factions in Combination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>One</hi> is ſo full of the Spirit of the World, and ſo tempo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rizing and compliant to the Powers of the World, and with their Prudentials, which is nothing elſe but the Wiſdom of the World, ſuch corrupters of the Simplicity and Generoſity of the Chriſtian Religion, in their Explications, and Betrayers of Souls and States into Sin, that if the other prevail to get the Power into their hands, there is little doubt to be made of their Compliance, whatever the Religion be which they ſet up; be it Deiſm, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm, or whatever elſe. I know one of them, who objected ſuch Matters of Conſcience againſt his Acceptance of a Preferment propoſed to him, that I could not in Conſcience perſwade him to accept it, and yet ſoon after he did accept it, and holds it too to this day, with another of it ſelf, a ſufficient Charge for any man of Conſcience to undertake. I have known the ſame Perſon very warmly reprove a Maſter of a Family for not allowing his Family the Uſe of ſuch Pomps and Vanities of the World, as he thought renounced in their Baptiſm, very diſagreeable to the Example and Precepts of our Saviour, his Apoſtles, and the Primitive Chriſtians, and of evil Conſequence to the living of moſt People; and thereby encourage them to live in Diſobedience to his Grief, and their Shame and Prejudice. And yet this Man paſſes for a good Man. To the Author of the Appeal, <hi>It looks like</hi> Madneſs <hi>to attach a Religion, when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152415:8"/>the Religion of the Country; when it has the Eſtabliſhment of the Laws of the Conſtitutions:</hi> And in his Wiſdom, ſuch Zeal for the Souls <hi>that</hi> Newgate <hi>could not eſcape their Diligence,</hi> is an Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of a Crime of the Prieſts; and ſuch a Crime it is as ſuch good Men are little guilty of; and might be aſhamed to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a Matter ſo reproachful to themſelves. Such Prudentials as theſe have been noted by others in their late Patriarch, and may eaſily be traced to their Original, in their Protopatriarch himſelf. And ſuch Agreement there is in ſome of their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples with Mr. <hi>Hobbe</hi>'s, and ſuch kindneſs have they common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed to one of the moſt Active Promoters of Socinianiſm, that their Complyance and Officiouſneſs to <hi>the other Faction,</hi> if they ſucceed, is not to be queſtioned.</p>
               <p>And for the <hi>other Faction,</hi> which lay concealed for a time among many Honeſt well-meaning Men in the <hi>long Parliament,</hi> and hath lain concealed among many ſuch, call'd Whiggs, in the <hi>late Reigns,</hi> it preſently appeared after this King came in, how they ſtood affected to Religion; and is now ſince the Peace apparent enough, how they ſtand affected to the Government too: Both might eaſily be perceiv'd by ſuch as have had Admittance to the Calves Head Club, and to Mr. <hi>Toland</hi>'s Clubs before now: But now appear bare-faced enough, ſo that they are no Myſteries. And the <hi>Whiggs</hi> are now commonly reputed the verieſt Knaves of the Nation by many Honeſt Men, who were heretofore taken to be of their Party. While I was wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this, I took notice in a Bookſellers-Shop of this Title of a Book, <hi>A brief History of the Times,</hi> which opening at page 40. I caſt my Eye upon theſe Words: <hi>The Plot-Faction Deſign'd the Ruine of the late King; and to compaſs it by leaving him neither Money, Power, Credit, nor Friends.</hi> And when I had looked far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into it, I obſerved ſuch Agreement between what is there related, then to have been, and what I am ſatisfied now is in Agitation, as do mutually confirm the Truth each of other, and doth fully ſatisfy me of <hi>the Mystery of the late Pretence and Clamours of the growth of Popery,</hi> to be no other than to Affront the King (as I was told expreſly by a Perſon lately deceas'd, who had as much reaſon to know as any one I know) to leſſen his Reputation with his Confederates abroad, and the Affections of the People to him at Home; to draw their Hearts to themſelves, and Abuſe and Amuſe them with that Pretence, while they compaſs their own Deſigns of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Religion to Deiſm, and the true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152415:8"/>to a Commonwealth, moſt like to end in Anarchy and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, as it did before. And whoſoever ſhall well conſider that Book (which I Confeſs I had never ſeen before) will there find ſuch Truths ſo unanſwerably aſſerted, as will both ſatisfy him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Truth of what I ſay here, and make him more cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and more wiſe than to be any more impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by ſo wicked, and groſs an Abuſe and Deceit, but rather turn his Indignation againſt ſuch Impoſtors and Diſturbers of the Peace of his Country.</p>
               <p>Theſe things I take to be all Truths, and ſuch Truths, as I thought my ſelf obliged to declare: I have endeavoured faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to diſcharge my Duty; and now leave it freely to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to judge as they think fit, and to the Conſequences of their own Judgment. Nor have I written any thing here out of ill will to any, but out of good will to my Country, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to thoſe very Perſons, who may be thought to be moſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and moſt ſharply reproved; and in due order to them, to whom I have performed my Duty before in private; whoſe Reformation I deſire; but not Confuſion, other than truly Penitential. And ſuch Fruits as theſe, are they, by which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Saviour's Rule, the Tree is to be known.</p>
               <p>I know no <hi>Sin</hi> more <hi>Epidemical</hi> and common in this Nation at this time among ſuch as make Profeſſion of Religion, than that, which by the Puniſhment denounced in the Goſpel, ſeems one of the greateſt, Diſowning or not owning Chriſt or his Words, for Fear, or Shame, or worldly Compliance: And none more noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly Guilty than <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> and <hi>Nemine contradicente</hi> Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. It was in my Mind, when I was Writing the Letter now Publiſhed, that ſhould Almighty God let loſe ſome of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences upon them, we ſhould ſoon have more <hi>Hamdens</hi> amongſt them. Nor ſhould I have mentioned it now but to prevent ſo great a Miſchief, and put them in mind to conſider the things which belong to their Peace in time, confeſs their Faults, give Glory to God, and expiate their Former Miſcarriages by ſo much the more generous Acts of Chriſtian Magnanimity upon all Occaſions hence forward.</p>
               <p>To ſuch as are apt to Aſſault me with their ſpiteful <hi>Argumentum ad Hominem</hi> concerning my Authority, when they have well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what I have to ſay to for my ſelf, I ſhall recommend to their Conſideration for their own ſelves what is well ſaid in an ill Hiſtory of the Reformation upon the Queſtions in the Book of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And with that I ſhall Conclude, as followeth, <hi>An</hi> 1550.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152415:9"/>in the Abſtract p. 118. which the Reader may ſee more at large in the Hiſtory, p. 145.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There were ſome</hi> Sponſions <hi>promiſed, as a Covenant, to which the Ordination was a Seal: The</hi> firſt <hi>of theſe was, That the Perſons that came to receive Orders, profeſsed that they believed they were</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly moved <hi>to it by the Holy Ghoſt. If this were well conſidered, it would no doubt put many that thirst after Sacred Offices to a ſtand; who, if they examine themſelves well, dare not pretend to that, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, perhaps they know nothing, but that they have it not: and if they make the Anſwer preſcrib'd in the Book, without feeling any ſuch Motion in their Heart, they do</hi> publickly Lye to God, and againſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>and have no reaſon to expect a Bleſſing on Orders ſo obtained. But too many conſider that only as</hi> a Ceremony in Law, <hi>neceſſary to make them capable of ſome Place of Profit, and not as the Dedication of their Lives and Labours to God, and to the gaining of Souls. It were happy for the Church, if Biſhops would not think it enough barely to put theſe Queſtions, but would uſe great ſtrictneſs in examining before-hand the Motives that ſet on thoſe who come to be Ordained.</hi> Another <hi>Sponſion is, that the Prieſts ſhall</hi> teach the People, <hi>committed to their Charge, and exhort them both in private and publick, and Viſit the Sick. By this they plight their Faith to God, for the care of Souls, to be managed by them in Perſon, and upon that they muſt find the Paſtoral Care to be a Load indeed: and ſo will neither deſert their Flocks, nor hire them out to weak, and perhaps Scandalous Mercenaries. In which the faultineſs of ſome have brought a blemiſh on this Church, and given ſcandal to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who could not have been ſo eaſily perſwaded to divide from it, if it had not been, that they were prejudiced by ſuch groſs and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Abuſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
